Preliminary Guide to the Charles F. Roos Papers, 1932-2013, bulk 1932-1958 RL.10041
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles F. Roos papers
1932-2013, bulk dates 1932-1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roos, Charles Frederick
RL.10041
5.5 Linear Feet Nine boxes.
Charles Roos (1901-1958) was the founder of Applied Econometrics, Inc. (now The Econometric Institute, Inc.). This collection documents the first 20 years of that organization through their publications and Roos' correspondence. It forms parts of the Economists' Papers Archive.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. Collection requires additional arrangement, description, and/or screening because it has been minimally processed. Contact Research Services for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials in this collection are electronic records that require special equipment. Contact Research Services with questions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles F. Roos papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as gifts in 2009 and 2013.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Frederick Roos (1901-1958) was a white American research and academic economist. He graduated with a PhD from the Rice Institute in 1926 and taught at Cornell University (1928-1931) and Colorado College (1934-1937). He was director of research at the National Recovery Administration (1933-1934) and Cowles Commission (1934-1937). He left to assume a business research position and founded Applied Economics, Inc. in 1938 (now The Econometrics Institute, Inc.). He was also one of the founders of the Econometric Society and eventually became president in 1948.
Scope and Contents
Accession 2009-0146 largely consists largely of reports and studies by Applied Econometrics for various clients, including railroads, paper companies, copper, newspaper, and electric power. Also includes working papers and charts, offprints and reprints, Economic Measures publications, some correspondence, and other miscellaneous material related to Roos' work, especially post-World War II.
Accession 2013-0024 contains additional reports, studies, and internal correspondence from Applied Econometrics and the Index Number Institute; volumes of Economic Measures and other publications; a photograph of Roos; and a single reel-to-reel audiotape.
Econometrics; Economic forecasting -- United States -- Econometrics; Economics, Mathematical; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Cowles Commission for Research in Economics; Econometric Institute (New York, N.Y.); Econometric Society; Economists' Papers Archive; Roos, Charles Frederick
- Accession 2009-0146, 1930s-1950s
  Scope and Contents
  Largely reports and studies by Applied Econometrics for various clients, including railroads, paper companies, copper, newspaper, and electric power. Also includes working papers and charts, offprints and reprints, Economic Measures publications, some correspondence, and other miscellaneous material related to Roos' work, especially post-World War II.
  - Econometric Institute material, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Booklet on services furnished to clients (Box 1)
    - Ledger sheet of Institute clients, Dec. 31, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper and magazine clients of Index Number Institute (Box 1)
    - Bank and other companies who were clients of Index Number Institute on May 5, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Roos and Von Szeliski: Demand for Durable Goods (Box 1)
    - Non-ferrous metal report, Sept. 1949 (Box 1)
    - Retail Trade report, Feb. 1949 (Box 1)
    - Beer report, June 1950 (Box 1)
    - Pittsfield Community Study, Sept. 1948 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Podea's work as international economic consultant to India, post-Institute (International Technical Development) (Box 1)
  - Bound list of clients, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Institute correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Charles Roos' death, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Economic Measures (various reports and papers) (Box 1)
  - Various books from the Institute Library (Box 1)
  - Loose-leaf notebook with working papers (1944-1947) and Economic Measures (1947) (Box 1)
  - Notebook with charts used by C.F. Roos at the NAM, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Notebook with Outlook for Retail Trade, Oct. 15, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Outlook for Retail Trade, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Economic Measures (various reports and papers) (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Econometric Institute reports and studies
    - Petroleum Industry (Box 2)
    - Newsprint (Box 2)
    - Income Payments (Box 2)
    - Retail Trade (Box 2)
    - Paper Industry (Box 2)
    - Copper (Box 3)
    - Electric Power (Box 3)
    - Railroad (Box 3)
    - Jewelry Sales (Box 3)
    - Railroad Equipment (Box 3)
  - Punchcard operation manual, 1942 (Box 3)
  - World Resources and Energy (coal study) (Box 3)
  - Banking memoranda, 1940s-1950s (Box 3)
  - Kaiser-Frazer operation (Box 3)
  - Wood Pulp Study, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Monsanto Chemical tax relief (Box 3)
  - Economic Measures charts, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Economic Measures, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Newsprint Problem, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Union Bag study, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Construction Industry report, undated (Box 4)
  - Beer Industry (Box 4)
  - Wood Rosin and Fir Doors demand, 1940s (Box 4)
  - Notebook with various econometric reports (Box 4)
  - Economic Measures, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Circulation study, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Various Institute reports, correspondence, and charts (Box 4)
  - Defiance Machine Works (Box 4)
  - Econometric Meeting, 1932 (Box 4)
  - General Outlook American Economy, 1949-1960 and Statistics and Economics of Housing (Box 4)
  - Various reports and off-prints, 1930s-1950s (Box 5)
  - Economic Measures (Box 6)
    - Volumes 12 - 13, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 13 (Box 6)
    - Volume 14, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 15, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 16, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 19, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 20, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Volume 21 (Box 6)
    - Summary, 1948 (Box 6)
  - Index Number Institute work papers, stock certificates and corporate minutes, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Studies on 14 basic industries, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Institute of Applied Econometrics lead industry report, 1942 (Box 6)
  - Internal work papers, 1940-1944 (Box 6)
  - Institute of Applied Econometrics reports on various industries, 1942, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Internal correspondence and reports, 1940-1949 (Box 6)
  - Measuring Business Cycles by Arthur Burns and Wesley Mitchell, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Here's the Record, 1938-1947 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous personnel records and notes (Box 7)
  - Publicaations by Charles Roos (Box 7)
  - Irving Fisher article, 1934 (Box 7)
  - Business Tides, 1941 (Box 7)
  - National Income by Paul Boschan, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Photograph of Charles Roos (Box 7)
  - Economic Measures basic indexes and forecasting techniques, 1944 to 1950 (Box 8)
  - Book of charts and calculations, 1919 - 1938 and internal work papers, 1945 (Box 9)
- Accession 2013-0024, 1940s
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Some materials are electronic records that require special equipment. Contact Research Services with questions.
  Additional reports, studies, and internal correspondence from Applied Econometrics and the Index Number Institute; volumes of Economic Measures and other publications; a photograph of Roos; and a single audioreel.
  - Audiovisual Material, 2013
    Access note. Subseries contains electronic records that require special equipment. Contact Research Services with questions.
    - The Roos Family - Perspectives on Econometrics, FDR's First Term, and More, 2013; 40 minutes (Video-file RL10041-MP4-0001.mp4)
      From the slate introducing the video: "In this interview, shot in 2013, Charles E. Roos, age 85, reflects on the work of his late father, Charles F. Roos. His father wa sa key economist for President Franklin Delano Roosevelt at the start of FDR's first term, and one of the founders of econometrics. Charlie then discusses his mother, Mary Barkuloo Roos, who also worked for FDR, and Charlies own work in physics. The interview takes place at the Roos home in Nashville, Tennessee. The interviewer is Jon Shayne, a family friend."
      - Edited video master, MP4 file, 2013, 40 minutes (Video-file RL10041-MP4-0001.mp4)